Guide to the Hotel St. George collection ARC.100
Brooklyn Historical Society
Hotel St. George collection
1930-1990
1982-1986
Brooklyn Historical Society
Hotel St. George (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.100
1.96 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box and one oversize box.
A collection of documents and photographs related to the Hotel St. George and dated 1930 to 1990, with the bulk of materials falling within the years 1982 to 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeff Ghitelman, May 22, 1990.
Photo album (1939) donated by John Prizeman in 2018.
Historical note
The block of buildings in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn that are collectively known as the Hotel St. George once comprised the largest hotel in New York City. Its constituent buildings were built between 1885 and 1929 on the block bounded by Clark, Pineapple, Hicks, and Henry Streets. Its primary building, the St. George Tower, once attracted celebrities, professional athletes, and presidential candidates, and boasted the Colorama Ballroom (at one time known as the largest banquet room in the world), as well as the largest salt water swimming pool in the United States.
The last remaining portion of the Hotel St. George that operated as a hotel was burnt down in 1995. As of 2010, the St. George Tower operates as a residential cooperative building, while the 100 Henry Street entrance (also known as the Weller Wing) and the 55 Clark Street entrance are now both part of Educational Housing Services (EHS), which offers dormitory services to students of many New York City colleges and universities. The buildings that comprise the Hotel St. George are protected under the New York City Landmarks Preservation Law.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Scope and Contents
The Hotel St. George collection spans the dates 1930 to 1990, with the bulk of materials falling within the years 1982 to 1986. Included in the collection are floorplans of the Hotel St. George, circa 1930-1950; a schematic rendering of the hotel building complex, circa 1930-1950; a photocopy of a Hotel St. George promotional brochure, 1932; an advertisement for Vinold Reiss Studios, the designers of the interior of the hotel, 1930; a copy of the hotel manager's stationery, circa 1930-1950; postcards (V1989.30.1 - .19) depicting the hotel's exterior, interiors, and pool, circa 1930s; and several black and white photographic slides (V1989.30.20 - .23) that depict banquets held in the hotel's ballrooms in 1932; and a 1939 album of interiors of the hotel, including the Grand Ballroom, the swimming pool, resturants and individual hotel rooms.
The materials that comprise the bulk date span of the collection consist primarily of copies of the St. George News and Views, a newsletter written and published by the St. George Tower Tenants' Association. These materials mostly document the process of converting the St. George Tower into a cooperative residential building during the 1980s, as well as providing insight into the daily lives of the building's residents. Also included are clippings from various New York City newspapers that document the St. George Tower's co-op conversion process, as well as life in the surrounding neighborhood during this period.
Arrangement
The collection is not arranged in any particular order.
Existence and Location of Copies
This collection (except for the floor plans and the St. George News and Views Newsletter) has been digitized and is available on our digital collections.
Related Materials
The Center for Brooklyn History holds related materials in the following collections:
- Early Brooklyn and Long Island photograph collection (ARC.201)
- Brooklyn photograph and illustration collection (ARC.202)
Apartment houses -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Architectural drawings; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Floor plans; Hotels -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Housing, Cooperative -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Newsletters; Photographs; Picture postcards; Real property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Tenants' associations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hotel St. George (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Winold Reiss Studios advertisement, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Schematic drawing of Hotel St. George block, circa 1930 (Box OS-23, Folder 1)
- Hotel St. George floor plan, circa 1930 (Box OS-23, Folder 2)
- Hotel St. George promotional pamphlet, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Slides, circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Arrangement
  The slides in this folder are arranged by object ID V1989.30.20 - .22
- Hotel St. George photo album, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Postcards, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  The postcards in this folder are organized by object ID numbers: V1989.30.1 - .19.
  Scope and Contents
  Several of the postcards do not depict the St. George Hotel. V1989.30.2 depicts Hotel Margaret in Brooklyn Heights and V1989.30.16 depicts The Towers Hotel at 25 Clark Street in Brooklyn Heights. V1989.30.19 depicts a building named St. George Hotel, but is likely not the one in Brooklyn.
- Mechanical of letterhead, circa 1940 (Box OS-23, Folder 3)
- Hotel St. George newspaper clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- St. George News and Views, Newsletter of the St. George Tower Tenants' Association, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- St. George News and Views, Newsletter of the St. George Tower Tenants' Association, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- St. George News and Views, Newsletter of the St. George Tower Tenants' Association, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- St. George News and Views, Newsletter of the St. George Tower Tenants' Association, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- St. George News and Views, Newsletter of the St. George Tower Tenants' Association, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)